Guide to the Archives of the Soviet communist party and Soviet state microfilm collection: Russian State Archives of Social and Political History (Rossiiskii gosudarstvennyi arkhiv sotsialno-politicheskoi istorii - RGASPI)
Hoover Institution Archives
- Fond 17, The Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union records, 1903-1965; 1971; 2,457 reels
  - Opis 1: Records of the Central Committee of The Russian Social-Democratic Labor Party (1903-1905), 5 reels) (Reel 2.56-2.60)
    - Letter from [V. A. Noskov], L. [G.] Deich, and [A. Paikes], to [V. D.] Bonch-Bruevich re inspection and reception of the files of the RSDRP dispatch office, 1904 September (Reel 2.60, File 294*)
    - Letter from [V. A. Noskov] to [M. N.] Liadov, confirming reception and approval of the account of the RSDRP cash-box for July 10 - September 15, 1904, 1904 September (Reel 2.60, File 295*)
    - Letter from [V. A. Noskov] to [V. D.] Bonch-Bruevich re the meeting with Popova, 1904 September (Reel 2.60, File 296)
    - Letter from V. [D.] Bonch-Bruevich to L. G. Deich re failure of the TsK RSDRP to fulfill its obligations to the editorial board of the magazine Rassvet, 1904 October (Reel 2.60, File 297)
    - Letter from V. [D.] Bonch-Bruevich to [V. A. Noskov] protesting the deliberate delay with the typesetting of manuscripts for issues 8-9 of the magazine Rassvet and requesting that either the typesetting be sped up or TsK debts to the Rassvet editorial board be settled, 1904 October (Reel 2.60, File 298)
    - Resolution of the representatives of the workers of Balakhanskii, Sabunchinskii, and Romaninskii raion of the city of Baku [sent to the TsK RSDRP] protesting expulsion of brothers L., N., and K. Shendrikov from the RSDRP Committee of Baku, 1904 October (Reel 2.60, File 299*)
    - Letter from L. [G.] D[eich] to V. M. Velichkina re financial issues connected with the dispatch office, 1904 October (Reel 2.60, File 300)
    - Letter from N. Bakh to [N. K. Krupskaia] re the letter from [V. P. Nogin] and others detained in Taganskaia prison, with their request for information about the situation in the party and about current events, 1904 October (Reel 2.60, File 301*)
    - Draft letter from [M. N.] Liadov on behalf of the émigré branch of the TsK RSDRP to the RSDRP Committee in Viatka re organizational issues, 1904 October (Reel 2.60, File 302*)
    - Report to the TsK RSDRP on the activities of the RSDRP Committee in Kazan from December, 1903, through October, 1904 (Reel 2.60, File 303*)
    - Letter from [G. D.] Leitaizen to the TsK RSDRP protesting the coup d'état in the TsK, etc., 1904 October (Reel 2.60, File 304*)
    - Letter from Sokolov to V. D. Bonch-Bruevich re reception of cash from Kleidman, etc., 1904 October (Reel 2.60, File 305)
    - Inscription on the envelope (address of V. D. Bonch-Bruevich in French), made by P. [B.] Akselrod, 1904 October (Reel 2.60, File 306)
    - Letter from V. [D.] Bonch-Bruevich to the RSDRP dispatch office re delivery and distribution of social-democratic literature and other related issues, 1904 October (Reel 2.60, File 307)
    - Statement of the Menshevik representatives expressing confidence in the TsK RSDRP and claiming termination of the isolation of the Mensheviks in the RSDRP; statement of the TsK about unification of the TsK with the Mensheviks and about future participation of the Mensheviks in party work, 1904 October (Reel 2.60, File 308*)
    - Letter from [A. I. Liubimov] to [V. A. Noskov] re position of local committees towards the 'July declaration' of the TsK, re results of the conference of twenty two Bolsheviks, re preparation for the Third Party Congress, and re Lenin's work in the Iskra editorial board, 1904 October (Reel 2.60, File 309)
    - Letter from V. [D.] Bonch-Bruevich to [V. A. Noskov] demanding that he publish in issue 76 of the newspaper Iskra the report of the RSDRP dispatch office for August - first half of September, 1904, 1904 October (Reel 2.60, File 310)
    - Letter from V. [D.] Bonch-Bruevich to the RSDRP dispatch office demanding an account of the dispatch office for delivered issues of the magazine Rassvet and reimbursement of money given to the TsK by the Rassvet editorial board, 1904 November (Reel 2.60, File 311)
    - Protocol of the meeting of the TsK RSDRP members re political activities of the TsK, re ties of the TsK with the Central Organ (Iskra), re concerted actions with BUND and Latvian social democracy, re issues connected with the local RSDRP organizations in Riga and Voronezh, re reports to be submitted to the Executive Committee, and re unification of technical institutions of the TsK, 1904 November 6 (Reel 2.60, File 312)
    - Report of [V. A. Noskov] to the TsK RSDRP about his activities as member of the Central Committee from the date of the Second RSDRP Congress through November 1, 1904, 1904 November 9 (Reel 2.60, File 313)
    - Draft record of the meeting of the members of the TsK RSDRP re convocation of a conference of party professional workers, re tasks and needs of professional party work, re work of the local RSDRP organizations, re establishment of social-democratic groups under the TsK RSDRP, re responsibilities assumed by TsK members, etc., 1904 October (Reel 2.60, File 314)
    - Resolution of the RSDRP Committee in Riga sent to the TsK RSDRP the publishing house for social-democratic literature run by V. Bonch-Bruevich and V. I. Lenin, expressing its support for the Bolsheviks, and requesting delivery of Bolshevik literature, 1904 October (Reel 2.60, File 315*)
    - Letter from [Iu. O. Martov] to [A. I. Liubimov] re refusal of the Mensheviks to follow the directives of the TsK RSDRP and re conditions for the agreement between the TsK RSDRP and the Central Organ (Iskra), 1904 November (Reel 2.60, File 316)
    - Letter from the RSDRP Committee in Riga responding to the representative of the TsK in Geneva with regard to his refusal to deliver social-democratic literature of the Bolsheviks, 1904 November (Reel 2.60, File 317*)
    - Note of Petr[?] re approval, at the TsK RSDRP request, of two members of the RSDRP Committee in Tula, 1904 November (Reel 2.60, File 318)
    - Protocol and resolution of the meeting of the TsK RSDRP re results of the conference with the representatives of the Mensheviks and transfer of the Menshevik [undercover] connections to the TsK, re political and operational management of the party, re establishment of the Bureau of the TsK, re responsibilities assumed by the TsK members, etc., 1904 November (Reel 2.60, File 319)
    - Letters of the TsK members [V. A. Noskov, L. B. Krasin, and L. E. Galperin] to M. A. Silvin, I. S. Vilenskii, and to the Party Council re resolution of the TsK about the work of the dispatch office and the printing office under the guidance of the TsK, re opposition of V. I. Lenin to co-optation of [I. F.] Dubrovinskii, [L. Ia.] Karpov, and [A. I.} Liubimov to the TsK, and re some organizational issues, 1904 November (Reel 2.60, File 320)
    - Letter from O. Minor to Vladimir Vasilievich expressing the author's suspicion that Kostia Sapetov is a traitor and agent provocateur, 1904 November (Reel 2.60, File 321)
  - Opis 2: Plenums of the VKP(b) Central Committee, 1918-1941, 88 reels) (Reel 2.2435-2.2457, Reel 2.2603-2.2638, Reel 2.2708-2.2736)
    Opis 2 contains protocols, verbatim records, and stenographic reports of TsK VKP(b) plenary meetings that took place from March, 1918, through February, 1941, and materials prepared for these meetings. Plenary meetings were held with participation of all TsK members and candidate members between party congresses and conferences. The most important issues of the policies of the KPSS and of the Soviet state were discussed and decided at the plenums. Resolutions of plenums were mandatory for both party organs and state organs and institutions. A considerable part of the resolutions and decisions adopted by the said plenums were published in the Soviet periodicals of that time and were later included in the book "KPSS in Resolutions and Decisions of Congresses, Conferences, and Plenums of the TsK" (editions I-VII). Six hundred seventy-seven (677) files (of 845 comprising this opis) were microfilmed for the Hoover Institution. The documents are divided into two parts: part I containing protocols and verbatim records of TsK VKP(b) plenary meetings, and part II (exempt from microfilming) containing correspondence related to the summoning of plenary meetings and materials pertaining to the issues to be considered and discussed at TsK VKP(b) plenary meetings (total of 88 reels). Within parts I and II the material is organized in chronological order by meeting. Part I is divided into 12 subseries according to the convocations of plenums (from the seventh through the eighteenth convocation). This opis also includes minutes of the meetings of the TsK RKP(b) Bureau (December 1918), of the TsK Conference of June 1919, of the private conference of the TsK members of December 30, 1920, of the joint meeting of the TsK and the RKP(b) committee of the city of Moscow, and of the joint meeting of the TsK and the TsKK (Central Control Commission) with the representatives of ten party organizations of October 25-27, 1923. Minutes of the TsK plenum commissions that were working during TsK meetings are also included in this opis. Protocols of the TsK meetings for 1918-1919 are incomplete. Starting with January 1924, verbatim records are included in this opis. The materials pertaining to the plenary meeting are presented in the following order: protocol, verbatim record edited by the authors, unedited verbatim record, and stenographic report (printed), if any. Each file comes with an internal list of documents in Russian. The Russian finding aid can be found on reel 2.15.
    I. Protocols and verbatim records of plenary meetings of the Central Committee of the VKP(b), convocations VII - XVII
    - 1. Seventh Convocation (1918 March-1919 March)
      - Protocols of the meetings of the TsK RKP(b) and the TsK Bureau of March 15 and May 19, 1918; protocol of the meetings of the TsK RKP(b) of September 16, 1918, with related materials; protocols of the meetings of the TsK RKP(b) of October 2, 22, 22 and 25, 1918; of December 17 and 19, 1918; and of January 16, February 4-5, March 14-20, 1919, 1918 March-1919 March (Reel 2.2435, File 1-14)
    - 2. Eighth Convocation (1919 March-1920 April)
      - Protocols and related materials of the meetings of the TsK RKP(b) Plenum of March 25, April 13, and May 4, 1919; protocol of the TsK RKP(b) Conference of June 7, 1919; protocols of the meetings of the TsK RKP(b) of June 10-15 and September 21, 1919; protocols of the meetings of the TsK RKP(b) plenums of July 3-4, September 26, and November 29, 1919; protocols of the meetings of the TsK and the TsK Bureau of January 16 and November 29, 1919; protocols of the meetings of the TsK RKP(b) plenums of January 31 and February 6, 1920, 1919 March-1920 February (Reel 2.2435, File 15-28)
    - 3. Ninth Convocation (1920 April-1921 March)
      - Protocols nos. 1-18 and related materials of the meetings of the TsK RKP(b) and TsK plenums, 1919 March-1920 December (Reel 2.2435, File 15-46)
      - Protocols nos. 19-30 and related materials of the meetings of the TsK RKP(b) plenums; protocol of the joint conference of the TsK and the Moscow City RKP(b) Committee, 1920 December-1921 March (Reel 2.2436, File 47-61)
    - 4. Tenth Convocation (1921 March-1922 April)
      - Protocols nos. 1-8, 8a, and 9-15 and related materials of the meetings of the TsK RKP(b) plenums, 1921 March-1922 March (Reel 2.2436, File 62-77)
    - 5. Eleventh Convocation (1922 April-1923 April)
      - Protocols nos. 1-11 and related materials of the meetings of the TsK RKP(b) plenums, 1922 April-1923 February (Reel 2.2436, File 78-88)
      - Protocols nos. 12-20 and related materials of the meetings of the TsK RKP(b) plenums, 1923 February-April (Reel 2.2437, File 89-97)
    - 6. Twelfth Convocation (1923 April-1924 May)
      - Protocols nos. 1-6 and related materials of the meetings of the TsK RKP(b) plenums of April 26, June 26-27, and September 23-25, 1923; protocols nos. 1-3 of the joint conference of the TsK, TsKK and representatives of Moscow, Petrograd, Ivanovo-Voznesensk, Nizhnii Novgorod, Kharkov, Donetsk, Yekaterinburg, Rostov, Baku, and Tula city RKP(b) committees of October 25-27, 1923; protocols nos. 7-8 and related materials of the meetings of the TsK RKP(b) Plenum of January 14-15, 1924; verbatim record of the session of the said TsK RKP(b) Plenum re date of opening and agenda of the Thirteenth Party Conference, re amnesty to esers (members of the Socialist-Revolutionary Party), re documents prohibited for circulation by the joint resolution of the TsK and TsKK plenums, re next tasks for party work, re results of the discussion and related leaflet, re the international situation, and re the currency reform; stenographic record of the meeting of the said Plenum re date of opening and agenda of the Thirteenth Party Conference, re amnesty to esers, re documents not allowed to circulate by the joint resolution of the TsK and TsKK plenums, re next tasks for party work, re results of the discussion and related leaflet, re the international situation, re the currency reform, re credits to be given to the military administration, re the statement of V. A. Antonov-Ovseenko, and re discussion of the TsK Politburo thesis on the next tasks of the economic policy, 1923 April-1924 January (Reel 2.2437, File 98-109)
      - Minutes of the emergency meeting of the TsK RKP(b)Plenum of January 22, 1924, re death of V. I. Lenin; protocol 10 of the TsK RKP(b) Plenum of January 29 - February 3, 1924, re Lenin's funeral, re salaries of the workers in the coal and metallurgical industries, re agricultural bank, re issues pertaining to the conclusion of the congress of Soviets, re speakers to deliver reports on industry and finance at the Congress, re assignments of positions in the Central Executive Commission, and re meeting of the [Bolshevik] faction at the Congress; protocol no. 11 of the meeting of the said Plenum re report on the international situation at the meeting of the [Bolshevik ] faction of the Congress of Soviets, re approval by the TsK of the resolutions of the Thirteenth RKP(b) Conference, re new appointments to the governing organs, re enlisting new party members among the ranks of bench-workers, re health care for top party officials, re reduction in prices [of consumer goods], re proposals of A. D. Tsuriupa, I. V. Stalin, L. B. Kamenev, N. I. Bukharin, M. M. Lashevich, and re release of information about TsK work; protocol no. 12 of the meeting of the said TsK Plenum; verbatim record of the session of the said TsK RKP(b) Plenum re terms of summoning the Twelfth Party Congress, re supplies for, enlistment into, and resignation from the army, and re budget of the military administration; stenographic report of the meeting of the said TsK RKP(b) Plenum re supplies for, enlistment into, and resignation from the army and the budget of the military administration, re terms of summoning the Twelfth Party Congress, and re approval of A. A. Andreev as Third Secretary of the TsK RKP(b); protocol nos. 13-15 of the TsK RKP(b) Plenum of March 31 - April 2, 1924, with related materials; verbatim record of the said TsK RKP(b) Plenum re talks between the USSR and Great Britain, re currency reform and representation quotas at the Twelfth Party Congress; verbatim record of the session of the TsK RKP(b) Plenum re military administration and re consumer cooperation and domestic trade; unedited verbatim records of the sessions of the said plenums, 1924 January-April (Reel 2.2438, File 110-123)
      - Protocols nos. 16-17 of the meetings of the TsK VKP(b) Plenum of March 31 - April 2, 1924, with related materials; verbatim record of the session of the said TsK RKP(b) Plenum pertaining to the concession Lena-Goldfields, to the Comintern, to the [party] work in villages, and to the composition and work of the TsKK (Central Control Committee); stenographic report of the meetings of the said TsK VKP(b) Plenum re the following issues: talks between the USSR and Great Britain, progress in the currency reform, the military administration, consumer cooperation and internal trade, the agenda of and representation at the Twelfth RKP(b) Congress, voting rights at the said Congress to be granted to those who joined the party after Lenin's death, the composition and activity of the TsKK, and the concession Lena-Goldfields; unedited verbatim records of the sessions of the TsK VKP(b) Plenum; protocol no. 18 of the meeting of the TsK RKP(b) Plenum of May 21, 1924; unedited verbatim records related to the said plenums, 1924 April-May (Reel 2.2439, File 124-129)
    - 7. Thirteenth Convocation (1924 June-1925 December)
      - Protocol no. 1 of the meeting of the TsK RKP(b) Plenum of June 2, 1925, re the following issues: elections to the TsKK RKP(b), representation of the TsK members at the TsKK meetings and TsKK representation at the TsK meetings, representation of the RKP(b) at the IKKI, the RKP(b) delegation at the Fifth Comintern Congress, assignments to the Politburo and the Organizational Bureau, assignments issued by the Twelfth Congress and its appeal to the workers and peasants, issues related to the agricultural bank, and maintenance of secrecy while handling [party] documents; protocol no. 2 of the meeting of the TsK RKP(b) Plenum of August 16-20, 1924; verbatim record of the session of the said TsK RKP(b) Plenum re talks between the USSR and Great Britain, and re the concessions Urkarta and Lena-Goldfields; protocol no. 3 of the meeting of the said TsK RKP(b) Plenum; verbatim record of the session of the said Plenum re the following issues: 1924-1925 USSR budget, report of the Politburo commission on the military budget, and the (cont.) situation in the army, 1924 June-August (Reel 2.2439, File 130-135)
      - Verbatim record (cont.) of the session of the TsK RKP(b) Plenum of August 16-20, 1924, on the 1924-1925 national and military budgets; protocols nos. 4-5 of the meetings of the said TsK RKP(b) Plenum; verbatim record of the session of the said TsK VKP(b) Plenum pertaining to the following issues: political education of new party members enlisted into the party after Lenin's death, report of the TsK and TsKK commission about salary, social security, and undercover work; verbatim record of the session of the said TsK VKP(b) Plenum pertaining to the policy towards the Amsterdam International of Trade Unions, to the composition of the Presidium of the Comintern, to the bread export as a resource to deal with the aftermath of the bad harvest and drought, to the participation of TsKK members in TsK RKP plenums, to the second party provincial conferences, and to the approval of D. A. Uglanov as TsK Secretary, 1924 August (Reel 2.2440, File 135-141)
      - Stenographic report of the meeting of the TsK RKP(b) Plenum of August 16-20, 1924, pertaining to the following issues: talks between the USSR and Great Britain, the concessions Urkarta and Lena-Goldfields, control figures for the 1924-1925 USSR budget, report of the TsK and TsKK on salary, social security, policy towards the Amsterdam International of Trade Unions, the aftermath of the bad harvest and drought, political education of new party members who joined the party after Lenin's death, and the second party conference held in provinces; protocols nos. 6 and 7 of the meeting of the TsK RKP(b) Plenum of October 25-26, 1924; verbatim record of the session of the said TsK RKP(b) Plenum re economic issues; verbatim record of the meetings of the said TsK RKP(b) Plenum re the following issues: discussion of the report on the economy, increase in the alcohol content of alcoholic beverages, British note in response to the "Zinoviev letter," national demarcation of Middle Asian republics, convocation of a party conference and congress and of a congress of Soviets, protest against the Politburo resolution appropriating two million more rubles of the budget of the Peoples Commissariat for Military Matters, struggle with poor harvest, and party work in villages; verbatim record of the session of the said TsK VKP(b) Plenum re party work in villages, and re events in Georgia; unedited verbatim records of the sessions of the said TsK plenums, 1924 August-October (Reel 2.2441, File 142-151)
      - Verbatim record (cont.) of the session of the TsK VKP(b) Plenum of October 25-27, 1924, re party work in villages and re events in Georgia; verbatim record of the session and stenographic report of the said TsK VKP(b) Plenum pertaining to the following issues: next economic tasks (taxation of agricultural products, bread procurements, import-export plan, etc.), increase in the alcohol content of alcoholic beverages, British note in response to the "Zinoviev letter," national demarcation of Middle Asian republics, convocation of a party conference and congress and of a congress of Soviets, protest against Politburo resolution appropriating two million rubles more to the budget of the Peoples Commissariat for Military Matters, next tasks for [party] work in villages, events in Georgia, local budgets, and struggle with the bad harvest and results of the work of the commission dealing with it; protocol no. 9 of the meeting of the TsK RKP(b) Plenum of January 17-18, 1925; verbatim records of the meeting of the said TsK RKP(b) Plenum reflecting the debates about Stalin's report on the resolution of local party organizations related to the speech by L. D. Trotsky; verbatim record of the session of the said TsK VKP(b) Plenum re the Sixteenth All-Union Party Conference, and the increase in budget; unedited verbatim records of the sessions of the said TsK RKP(b) plenums, 1924 October-1925 January (Reel 2.2442, File 151-158)
      - Verbatim record (cont.) of the session of the TsK RKP(b) Plenum of January 18-20, 1925, re the Sixteenth All-Union party conference and the increase in the budget; protocol 10 of the meeting of the said TsK RKP(b) Plenum; verbatim record of the sessions of the said TsK RKP(b) Plenum pertaining to the following issues: the Central Executive Committee (TsIK) and the Congress of Soviets, appropriations to the People's Commissariat for Military Matters, expanded Plenum of IKKI?, and the report on the situation in and prospects of the metallurgical industry; verbatim record of the session of the said TsK RKP(b) Plenum re discussion of the report on the situation in and prospects of the metallurgical industry, re report of the Organizational Bureau on the measures for strengthening [party] work among women workers and peasants, re concession for the development of the Chiaturskii region rich in magnum to be awarded by the Soviet Union to Harriman's company (US), re relations between the USSR and Great Britain, and re the situation with the youth [in the USSR]; unedited verbatim records of the sessions of the said TsK RKP(b) Plenum, 1925 January (Reel 2.2443, File 158-163)